is being able to understand intelligence by creating our own computational systems that display intelligence the way we see it in nature. Now, most popular views of AI, of course, come from science fiction and the movies, and I'm personally a big Star Wars fan. But that tends to be a very human-centric view of intelligence. When you think of a fish school, or when I think of a flock of starlings, that feels like a really different kind of intelligence. For starters, any one fish is just so tiny compared to the sheer size of the collective, so it seems that any one individual would have a really limited and myopic view of what's going on, and intelligence isn't really about the individual but somehow a property of the group itself. Secondly, and the thing that I still find most remarkable, is that we know that there are no leaders supervising this fish school. Instead, this incredible collective mind behavior is emerging purely from the interactions of one fish and another. Somehow, there are these interactions or rules of engagement between neighboring fish that make it all work out. So the question for AI then becomes, what are those rules of engagement that lead to this kind of intelligence, and of course, can we create our own? And that's the primary thing that I work on with my team in my lab. We work on it through theory, looking at abstract rule systems and thinking about the mathematics behind it. We also do it through biology, working closely with experimentalists. But mostly, we do it through robotics, where we try to create our own collective systems that can do the kinds of things that we see in nature, or at least try to. One of our first robotic quests along this line was to create our very own colony of a thousand robots. So very simple robots, but they could be programmed to exhibit collective intelligence, and that's what we were able to do. So this is what a single robot looks like. It's quite small, about the size of a quarter, and you can program how it moves, but it can also wirelessly communicate with other robots, and it can measure distances from them. And so now we can start to program exactly an interaction, a rule of engagement between neighbors. And once we have this system, we can start to program many different kinds of rules of engagement that you would see in nature. So for example, spontaneous synchronization, how audiences are clapping and suddenly start all clapping together, the fireflies flashing together. We can program rules for pattern formation, how cells in a tissue determine what role they're going to take on and set the patterns of our bodies. We can program rules for migration, and in this way, we're really learning from nature's rules. But we can also take it a step further. We can actually take these rules that we've learned from nature and combine them and create entirely new collective behaviors of our very own. So for example, imagine that you had two different kinds of rules. So your first rule is a motion rule where a moving robot can move around other stationary robots. And your second rule is a pattern rule where a robot takes on a color based on its two nearest neighbors. So if I start with a blob of robots in a little pattern seed, it turns out that these two rules are sufficient for the group to be able to self-assemble a simple line pattern. And if I have more complicated pattern rules, and I design error correction rules, we can actually create really, really complicated self assemblies, and here's what that looks like. So here, you're going to see a thousand robots that are working together to self-assemble the letter K. The K is on its side. And the important thing is that no one is in charge. So any single robot is only talking to a small number of robots nearby it, and it's using its motion rule to move around the half-built structure just looking for a place to fit in based on its pattern rules. And even though no robot is doing anything perfectly, the rules are such that we can get the collective to do its goal robustly together. And the illusion becomes almost so perfect, you know -- you just start to not even notice that they're individual robots at all, and it becomes a single entity, kind of like the school of fish. So these are robots and rules in two dimensions, but we can also think about robots and rules in three dimensions. So what if we could create robots that could build together? And here, we can take inspiration from social insects. So if you think about mound-building termites or you think about army ants, they create incredible, complex nest structures out of mud and even out of their own bodies. And like the system I showed you before, these insects actually also have pattern rules that help them determine what to build, but the pattern can be made out of other insects, or it could be made out of mud. And we can use that same idea to create rules for robots. So here, you're going to see some simulated robots. So the simulated robot has a motion rule, which is how it traverses through the structure, looking for a place to fit in, and it has pattern rules where it looks at groups of blocks to decide whether to place a block. And with the right motion rules and the right pattern rules, we can actually get the robots to build whatever we want. And of course, everybody wants their own tower. (Laughter) So once we have these rules, we can start to create the robot bodies that go with these rules. So here, you see a robot that can climb over blocks, but it can also lift and move these blocks and it can start to edit the very structure that it's on. But with these rules, this is really only one kind of robot body that you could imagine. You could imagine many different kinds of robot bodies. So if you think about robots that maybe could move sandbags and could help build levees, or we could think of robots that built out of soft materials and worked together to shore up a collapsed building -- so just the same kind of rules in different kinds of bodies. Or if, like my group, you are completely obsessed with army ants, then maybe one day we can make robots that can climb over literally anything including other members of their tribe, and self-assemble things out of their own bodies. Once you understand the rules, just many different kinds of robot visions become possible. And coming back to the snorkeling trip, we actually understand a great deal about the rules that fish schools use. So if we can invent the bodies to go with that, then maybe there is a future where I and my group will get to snorkel with a fish school of our own creation. Each of these systems that I showed you brings us closer to having the mathematical and the conceptual tools to create our own versions of collective power, and this can enable many different kinds of future applications, whether you think about robots that build flood barriers or you think about robotic bee colonies that could pollinate crops or underwater schools of robots that monitor coral reefs, or if we reach for the stars and we thinking about programming constellations of satellites. In each of these systems, being able to understand how to design the rules of engagement and being able to create good collective behavior becomes a key to realizing these visions. So, so far I've talked about rules for insects and for fish and for robots, but what about the rules that apply to our own human collective? And the last thought that I'd like to leave you with is that science is of course itself an incredible manifestation of collective intelligence, but unlike the beautiful fish schools that I study, I feel we still have a much longer evolutionary path to walk. So in addition to working on improving the science of robot collectives, I also work on creating robots and thinking about rules that will improve our own scientific collective. There's this saying that I love: who does science determines what science gets done. Imagine a society where we had rules of engagement where every child grew up believing that they could stand here and be a technologist of the future, or where every adult believed that they had the ability not just to understand but to change how science and technology impacts their everyday lives. What would that society look like? I believe that we can do that. I believe that we can choose our rules, and we engineer not just robots but we can engineer our own human collective, and if we do and when we do, it will be beautiful. Thank you. (Applause)
es ser capaz de entender la inteligencia creando nuestros propios sistemas que muestren inteligencia como la vemos en la naturaleza. Las opiniones más populares de IA, vienen de la ciencia ficción y las películas y yo soy una gran fan de Star Wars. Pero eso tiende a una visión de la inteligencia muy humana. Cuando se piensa en un banco de peces o en una familia de estorninos, se siente como otro tipo de inteligencia. Para empezar, cualquier pez es tan pequeño comparado con el tamaño total del colectivo que parece que cualquier individuo tendría un alcance realmente limitado y miope de lo que pasa. y la inteligencia no trata de individuos sino de alguna manera de una propiedad del grupo mismo. En segundo lugar, y lo que que todavía encuentro más notable, es que sabemos que no hay líderes supervisando estos peces. En vez de eso, este increíble comportamiento mental colectivo está emergiendo puramente de las interacciones de un pez y otro. De alguna manera, estas interacciones o reglas de juego entre peces vecinos hacen que todo funcione. Así que la pregunta para IA se convierte en: ¿cuáles son esas reglas de juego que llevan a este tipo de inteligencia? y claro, ¿podemos crear la nuestra? Y eso es lo principal en que trabajo con mi equipo en mi laboratorio. Trabajamos en ello a través de la teoría, mirando los sistemas de reglas abstractas y pensando en las matemáticas de fondo. También lo hacemos mediante la biología, en conjunto con los experimentalistas. Pero, sobre todo, a través de la robótica donde intentamos crear nuestros propios sistemas colectivos que puedan hacer el tipo de cosas como en la naturaleza, o al menos intentarlo. Una de nuestras primeras misiones robóticas en esta línea fue crear nuestra propia colonia de mil robots. Robots muy simples, pero que podrían ser programados para exhibir inteligencia colectiva, y eso es lo que pudimos hacer. Así que así es como se ve un robot. Es bastante pequeño, del tamaño de una moneda, y se puede programar cómo se mueven, pero también pueden comunicarse inalámbricamente con otros robots, y puede medir las distancias entre ellos. Ahora podemos empezar a programar exactamente una interacción, una regla de juego entre vecinos. Y una vez que tengamos este sistema, podemos empezar a programar diferentes tipos de reglas de juego. como se vería en la naturaleza. Así, por ejemplo, una sincronización espontánea, cómo aplaude el público y de repente empiezan a aplaudir juntos, las luciérnagas brillando juntas. Podemos programar reglas para la formación de patrones, cómo las células en un tejido determinar qué papel van a asumir y fijar los patrones del cuerpo. Podemos programar reglas para la migración, y de esta manera, aprendemos de las reglas de la naturaleza. Pero también podemos ir un paso más allá. Podemos tomar las reglas que hemos aprendido de la naturaleza y combinarlas y crear conductas colectivas completamente nuevas propiamente nuestras. Así que, por ejemplo, imaginen tener dos tipos diferentes de reglas. La primera regla es una de moción donde un robot en movimiento puede moverse alrededor de otros estáticos. Y la segunda regla es una regla patrón en que un robot toma el color de sus dos vecinos más cercanos. Así que si empiezo con una pizca de robots en una pequeña semilla patrón. resulta que estas dos reglas son suficientes para que el grupo pueda autoensamblarse en un simple patrón de líneas. Y si las reglas son más complicadas, y diseño reglas de corrección de errores, realmente podemos crear ensambles muy complejos, que se ven así. Así que aquí, van a ver miles de robots que trabajan juntos para ensamblar la letra K. La K está tumbada. Y lo importante es que nadie está al mando. Así que cualquier robot solo habla a un pequeño número de robots cercanos, y usa su regla de moción para moverse buscando un lugar para encajar basado en sus reglas del patrón. Y aunque ningún robot hace nada perfectamente, las reglas son tales que podemos conseguir colectivamente lograr el objetivo sólidamente juntos. Y la ilusión se convierte en casi tan perfecta, saben... que uno empieza a no darte cuenta de que son robots individuales y se convierten en una sola entidad, como el banco de peces. Estos son robots y reglas en dos dimensiones, pero también podemos pensar en robots y reglas en tres dimensiones. ¿Y si pudiéramos crear robots que podrían construir juntos? Y para eso podemos inspirarnos en los insectos sociables. Si piensan en termitas que construyen montículos o en ejércitos de hormigas. que crean estructuras increíblemente complejas de nidos de barro e incluso de sus propios cuerpos. Y como el sistema que mostré antes, estos insectos en realidad también tienen reglas de patrón que les ayudan a determinar qué construir, pero el patrón puede hacerse de otros insectos o de barro. Y podemos usar la misma idea para crear reglas para robots. Así que aquí pueden ver algunos robots simulados. donde el robot simulado tiene reglas para moverse con las que atraviesa la estructura, buscando un lugar para encajar, y tiene reglas de patrón donde se examinan grupos de bloques para decidir si colocar o no un bloque. Y con las correctas reglas de moción y de patrón podemos conseguir que los robots construyan lo que queramos. Y por supuesto, todo el mundo quiere su propia torre. (Risas) Así que cuando tengamos esas reglas, podemos empezar a crear los robots que sigan las reglas. Vean un robot que puede trepar los bloques, pero también puede levantarlos y moverlos y puede editar la propia estructura donde está. Pero con estas reglas, en realidad, este es solo uno de los cuerpos imaginables Pueden imaginarse diferentes tipos de cuerpos. Si piensan en robots que mueven sacos de arena para ayudar a construir diques, o en robots que construyen con materiales blandos trabajando juntos para apuntalar un edificio derrumbado... el mismo tipo de reglas en diferentes tipos de cuerpos. O si, como en mi grupo, completamente obsesionados con ejércitos de hormigas, quizás algún día podamos hacer robots que trepen sobre cualquier cosa incluyendo a miembros de su tribu, y ensamblar cosas de sus propios cuerpos. Una vez conocidas las reglas, se hacen posibles muchos tipos diferentes de visiones de robots. Y volviendo al viaje con esnórquel, realmente entendemos mucho de las reglas usadas por los bancos de peces. Así que si podemos inventar los cuerpos que vayan con eso, tal vez haya un futuro en el que mi grupo pueda nadar con peces creados por nosotros. Cada uno de los sistemas que les mostré nos acerca a tener las herramientas matemáticas y conceptuales para crear nuestras propias versiones del poder colectivo, permitiendo muchas clases diferentes de futuras aplicaciones. Ya bien si piensan en robots que construyen barreras contra inundaciones o en colonias de abejas robóticas que podrían polinizar los cultivos o escuelas submarinas de robots que monitorizan los arrecifes de coral, o si tratamos de alcanzar las estrellas y pensamos en programar constelaciones de satélites. En cada uno de estos sistemas, ser capaz de entender cómo diseñar las reglas del juego y ser capaz de crear buena conducta colectiva son clave para hacer cumplir estas visiones. Hasta ahora he hablado sobre normas para insectos y peces y para robots, ¿y de las reglas que se aplican a nuestro propio colectivo humano? El último pensamiento que me gustaría dejarles es que la ciencia es, por supuesto, ella misma una manifestación increíble de la inteligencia colectiva, pero a diferencia de los hermosos bancos de peces que estudio, siento que todavía nos queda un gran camino evolutivo por recorrer. Así que además de trabajar para mejorar la ciencia de los robots colectivos, también trabajo en la creación de robots y pensar en las reglas que mejorarán nuestra propia colectividad científica. Hay un dicho que me encanta: quien hace ciencia determina lo que la ciencia produce. Imaginen una sociedad con reglas de juego donde cada niño puede crecer pensando que puede estar aquí y ser un tecnólogo del futuro, o donde cada adulto crea tener la habilidad no solo para entender, sino para cambiar cómo la ciencia y la tecnología impactan en su vida cotidiana. ¿Cómo sería esa sociedad? Creo que podemos hacerlo. Creo que podemos elegir nuestras reglas, y nosotros como ingenieros no solo diseñamos robots, sino podemos hacer crear nuestro propio colectivo humano, y si lo hacemos y cuando lo hagamos, será hermoso. Gracias. (Aplausos)